华纳     兄弟    电影公司
时代华纳旗下公司
城 堡 石
电影娱乐公司
城  堡  石
出品
《如果我不在乎》·墨水点乐队
"If I Didn't Care" - The Ink Spots
∮ 如果我不在乎 ∮
∮ If I didn't care ∮
∮ 我就不会言不尽意 ∮
∮ More than words can say ∮
∮ 如果我不在乎 ∮
∮ If I didn't care ∮
∮ 我又怎能感同身受 ∮
∮ Would I feel this way? ∮
∮ 如果这不是爱 ∮
∮ If this isn't love ∮
∮ 为何我会颤抖 ∮
∮ Then why do I thrill? ∮
∮ 又是什么盘旋在我脑海 ∮
∮ And what makes my head go round and round ∮
∮ 而我初心仍在驻守 ∮
∮ While my heart stands still? ∮
∮ 如果我不在乎 ∮
∮ If I didn't cares ∮
∮ 结果是否照旧 ∮
∮ Would it be the same? ∮
∮ 我的每次祈祷 ∮
∮ Would my every prayer begin and end ∮
∮ 都以你的名字开头结束 ∮
∮ With just your name? ∮
∮ 且我依然深信 ∮
∮ And would I be sure ∮
∮ 这份爱无与伦比 ∮
∮ That this is love beyond compare? ∮
∮ 如果我不在乎 ∮
∮ Would all this be true ∮
∮ 这一切怎会成真 ∮
∮ If I didn't care for you? ∮
肖申克的救赎
领衔主演
蒂姆·罗宾斯
摩根·弗里曼
鲍   勃  ·  冈   顿
威 廉 姆  ·   赛 德 勒
克  兰  西  ·  布  朗
吉 尔 · 贝 罗 斯
马 克 · 罗 斯 顿
杰  弗  里 · 德  蒙  恩
拉 里 勃 兰 登 堡
布 莱 恩·利 比
尼 尔·君 图 力
戴 维·普 罗 瓦 尔
约 瑟 夫·拉 尼 奥
保 罗·麦 克 拉 伦
胡 德·西 科 利 亚
詹姆斯·惠特摩
饰 布鲁克斯·海特伦
选角导演
黛  博·拉  亚  居  拉
配 乐
托  马  斯·纽  曼
服装设计
伊丽莎白·麦克布赖德
艺  术  指  导
特  伦  斯·马   什
剪  辑
理查德·弗朗西斯·布鲁斯
摄     影     指     导
罗     杰  ·  狄     金     斯
监        制         人
利兹·格洛策
大卫·莱斯特
《丽塔·海沃斯与肖申克的救赎》
改编自史蒂芬·金所著短篇小说
编     剧
弗 兰 克 · 达 拉 邦 特
制   作   人
尼  基 · 马  文
导 演
弗 兰 克 · 达 拉 邦 特
吉时香烟（Chesterfield）
赫伍口中的“Yes, Richmond, Virginia.”
说的就是吉时香烟
在世界上有很高知名度，很高人气，历史也悠久
最初由德拉蒙德（DRUMMOND）烟草公司
创立于1873年，迄今已近150年
体制
可理解为包括某种规则、习惯、意识的环境
甚至是周围人的眼光、期许和评价
体制化
是指对这种环境的适应
达到“内化”的程度
从而形成一道熟视无睹的围墙
将自我禁锢其中
因此，体制化
可归纳为“过度顺应”
艾尔·卡彭（Al Capone）
绰号疤面（Scarface）
是一名美国黑帮成员
他在禁酒时期获得名气
成为芝加哥犯罪集团联合创始人和老大
芝华塔尼欧（Zihuatanejo）
墨西哥西南部的一座城市
其名在纳瓦特尔语中为“女人之地”
因为该地在古代是母系社会
该市因《肖申克的救赎》而声名大噪
罗伯特·弗罗斯特，美国诗人
素有“新英格兰诗人”之称，其诗朴素无华，舒畅自然
《桦树》节选——
“我真想离开人世一会儿
回来后再重新开始。
愿命运不再故意误解我
然后部分地成全我的希望，把我迅速
拿开而不送回。人世是个适合爱的地方：
我不知道还要去哪里会更好。
我会爬着一棵桦树而去，
从黑色的树枝攀爬到那向着天空的雪白
树干，直到那树已不再能够承受我，
并弯下自己的树梢再次把我送回来。
不管是离去还是返回我都会愉快。”
驳    回
一点心意
欢迎归来
主的审判会迅速降临
老布来此一游
如何修理任一汽车的任一部分
加戈头漫画
驳    回
瑞德 赠
十周年庆
布鲁克斯·海特伦图书纪念馆
肖申克监狱发生贪污谋杀
主 的 审 判
会 迅 速  降  临
你说得对
亲爱的典狱长
救赎之道 就在其中
你说得对
批      准
老布
到此一游
巴克斯顿
也来过
瑞德
谨此纪念艾伦·格林
校订·注释·特效
popxhy
修订基础
sunminghao字幕 钦腾字幕
杜弗伦先生  请描述
Mr. Dufresne, describe...
命案当晚你和妻子争吵的情形
the confrontation you had with your wife the night she was murdered.
我们吵得很凶
It was very bitter.
她说不怕我知道  她讨厌偷偷摸摸
She said she was glad I knew,that she hated all the sneaking around.
她还说  想去雷诺市办离婚
And she said that she wanted a divorce in Reno.
-你怎样回答?  -我拒绝离婚
-What was your response?  -I told her I would not grant one.
“你休想活着去雷诺市。”
"I'll see you in hell before I see you in Reno."
邻居作证你说过这句话
Those were your words, according to your neighbors.
也许吧
If they say so.
我气炸了  记不清楚
I really don't remember. I was upset.
你们吵完以后呢？
What happened after you argued with your wife?
她收拾行李
She packed a bag.
去跟昆汀住……
She packed a bag to go and stay with Mr. Quentin.
格伦·昆汀  乡村俱乐部的高尔夫球教练
Glenn Quentin, golf pro at the Snowden Hills Country Club...
你最近才发现  他是你太太的情夫
whom you had discovered was your wife's lover.
你跟踪她吗？
Did you follow her?
我先去酒吧买醉
I went to a few bars first.
然后去他家  但没人在
Later, I drove to his house to confront them. They weren't home.
我停了车
I parked in the turnout...
等他们
and waited.
用意何在？
With what intention?
我不确定
I'm not sure.
我醉了
I was confused...
糊里糊涂
drunk.
我想……
I think...
最多只是吓吓他们
mostly I wanted to scare them.
结果他们一回来  你就冲进屋杀了他们
When they arrived, you went up to the house and murdered them.
不  我逐渐酒醒
I was sobering up.
开车回家睡觉
I got back in the car and I drove home to sleep it off.
路中把枪丢入皇家河
Along the way, I threw my gun into the Royal River.
我已讲得很清楚
I've been very clear on this point.
但清洁妇隔天早晨上工时
I get hazy where the cleaning woman shows up the following morning...
发现床上的二人尸体
and finds your wife in bed with her lover...
身上满是点三八的弹孔
riddled with.38-caliber bullets.
你不觉得这很巧吗？  还是只有我这么想？
Does that strike you as a fantastic coincidence, or is it just me?
是很巧
Yes, it does.
但你仍声称早在案发之前
Yet you still maintain you threw your gun into the river...
就已丢弃了枪
before the murders took place.
这种说法倒是很省事
That's very convenient.
这是实话
It's the truth.
警方打捞三天都没找到
The police dragged that river for three days, and nary a gun was found...
这样就无法比对你的手枪和
so no comparison could be made between your gun and the bullets...
从受害人血尸内取出的弹头
taken from the bloodstained corpses of the victims.
所以呢
And that also...
这样也非常省事  不是吗  杜弗伦先生
is very convenient. Isn't it, Mr. Dufresne?
我是清白的
Since I am innocent of this crime...
所以找不到枪  反倒对我非常不利
I find it decidedly inconvenient that the gun was never found.
一切证据都向各位指明了案情
Ladies and gentlemen, you've heard all the evidence.
脚印和胎痕证明被告在场
We have the accused at the scene of the crime. We have footprints.
散落地面的子弹上有他的指纹
Bullets on the ground bearing his fingerprints.
酒瓶碎片上同样也有指痕
A broken bourbon bottle, likewise with fingerprints.
最重要的是
And most of all...
一位美女与情夫
we have a beautiful young woman and her lover...
相拥而死
lying dead in each other's arms.
他们是有伤风化
They had sinned.
但是
But was their crime so great...
罪该致死吗？
as to merit a death sentence?
与此同时  请各位
While you think about that...
再考虑一件事
think about this:
一只左轮手枪只能装六发子弹  而非八发
A revolver holds six bullets, not eight.
所以他并非一时冲动
I submit that this was not a hot-blooded crime of passion.
冲动即使不可宽恕  但尚可理解
That at least could be understood, if not condoned.
然而
No.
这是复仇
This was revenge...
残忍而冷血的谋杀  想想看
of a much more brutal, cold-blooded nature. Consider this:
这两人各中四枪
Four bullets per victim.
共八枪  而非六枪
Not six shots fired, but eight.
因此他是先射完一轮
That means that he fired the gun empty...
再装弹补上两枪
and then stopped to reload so that he could shoot each of them again.
一人添一枪
An extra bullet per lover...
射入脑袋
right in the head.
你面目冷漠  全无悔意  杜弗伦先生
You strike me as a particularly icy and remorseless man, Mr. Dufresne.
看见你就令我齿冷
It chills my blood just to look at you.
根据缅因州赋予我的权力
By the power vested in me by the state of Maine...
我判处你两次终身监禁
I hereby order you to serve two life sentences back-to-back...
分别为两位死者偿命  退庭！
one for each of your victims. So be it!
坐下
Sit.
根据你的材料 你的终身监禁已经服满20年
We see you've served 20 years of a life sentence?
-是的  -你改过自新了吗？
-Yes, sir.  -You feel you've been rehabilitated?
是的  完全改造好了
Yes, sir. Absolutely, sir.
我是说  我已吸取教训
I mean, I learned my lesson.
真的  我已洗心革面
I can honestly say that I'm a changed man.
我不会再做危害社会的事了
I'm no longer a danger to society.
我向上帝发誓
That's God's honest truth.
瑞德
Hey, Red.
怎样？
How'd it go?
还不是老样子
Same old shit, different day.
了解
Yeah, I know how you feel.
我下周也准备要吃闭门羹
I'm up for rejection next week.
我上周才假释被拒
Yeah, I got rejected last week.
很正常
It happens.
嗨，瑞德，借一包烟吧
Hey, Red, bump me a deck.
滚开  你欠我五包了
Get out of my face, man! You're into me for five packs already.
-四包  -五包
-Four!  -Five!
美国每个监狱里可能都会有我这样的人
There must be a con like me in every prison in America.
我能为你弄到各种东西
I'm the guy who can get it for you.
香烟啦  大麻啦
Cigarettes, a bag of reefer, if that's your thing...
孩子高中毕业想喝白兰地也行
bottle of brandy to celebrate your kid's high school graduation.
只要你想  几乎都没问题
Damn near anything within reason.
是的 先生  我就像百货公司
Yes, sir! I'm a regular Sears and Roebuck.
所以1949年当安迪·杜弗伦来找我
So when Andy Dufresne came to me in 1949...
问能否弄张丽塔·海华丝的海报进来时
and asked me to smuggle Rita Hayworth into the prison for him...
我二话不说  “没问题！”
I told him, "No problem."
到大门口集合
to the main gate
安迪在47年初进肖申克监狱
Andy came to Shawshank Prison...
罪名是杀害老婆和情夫
in early 1947 for murdering his wife and the fella she was banging.
他原本是缅因州一家大银行的副总裁
On the outside, he'd been vice president of a large Portland bank.
年轻有为  前程远大
Good work for a man so young.
来这里  瑞德
Here, Red.
听得懂英语吗？
You speak English, butt-steak?
跟这位长官走
You follow this officer.
我这辈子没看过这么多满脸晦气的窝囊废
I never seen such a sorry-Iooking heap of maggot shit in all my life.
菜鸟  过来
Hey, fish! Come over here!
打个赌吧  瑞德？
Taking bets today, Red?
赌烟还是赌钱？
Smokes or coin? Bettor's choice.
烟  我赌两根
Smokes. Put me down for two.
你挑哪个？
All right, who's your horse?
那个小个子
That little sack of shit.
-前面排第八  他会是第一个  -算你瞎眼  我赌了
-Eighth. He'll be first.  -Bullshit! I'll take that action.
你输定了
You're out some smokes, son.
你聪明  你挑呀
If you're so smart, you call it.
胖脸肥臀那个
I'll take that chubby fat-ass there.
第五个  我赌五根烟
The fifth one. Put me down for a quarter deck.
头名菜鸟大选日
Fresh fish today!
我们又有的玩啦
We're reeling them in!
说实话  当初我并不看好他
I admit I didn't think much of Andy first time I laid eyes on him.
弱不禁风
Looked like a stiff breeze would blow him over.
这是他给我的最初印象
That was my first impression of the man.
你挑谁？
What do you say?
面带富贵相的高个儿
That tall drink of water with the silver spoon up his ass.
他？  不可能啦
That guy? Never happen.
-我赌十根烟  -有种
-10 cigarettes.  -That's a rich bet.
谁要和我赌？
Who's going to prove me wrong?
赫伍？  渣哥？
Heywood? Jigger?
史基？
Skeets?
福洛？
Floyd!
你们输定了
Four brave souls.
回牢房准备点名
Return to your cellblocks for evening count.
全都回牢房
All prisoners, return to your cellblocks.
向右转
Turn to the right!
向前看
Eyes front.
他是看守长海利
This is Mr. Hadley. He's captain of the guards.
我是典狱长诺顿
I'm Mr. Norton, the warden.
你们被判有罪
You are convicted felons.
所以被送到这来
That's why they've sent you to me.
第一条规矩
Rule number one:
不许亵渎上帝
No blasphemy.
这里不准滥呼上帝之名
I'll not have the Lord's name taken in vain in my prison.
其它规矩……
The other rules...
你们以后就知道了  有问题吗？
you'll figure out as you go along. Any questions?
什么时候吃饭？
When do we eat?
我们叫你吃就吃
You eat when we say you eat.
叫你拉就拉  叫你撒就撒
You shit when we say you shit, and piss when we say you piss.
听明白了吗？人渣
You got that, you maggot-dick motherfucker?
站起来
On your feet.
我只相信两件事
I believe in two things:
纪律和圣经
Discipline and the Bible.
你们两样都少不了
Here, you'll receive both.
把信仰寄托神
Put your trust in the Lord.
把贱命交给我
Your ass belongs to me.
肖申克监狱欢迎各位
Welcome to Shawshank.
解铐
Unhook them.
转身
Turn around.
可以了
That's enough.
到笼子边上去
Move to the end of the cage.
转身  洒除虱粉
Turn around. Delouse him.
转身
Turn around.
出来  去领囚衣和圣经
Move out of the cage. Pick up your clothes and Bible.
下一个
Next man up!
向右
To the right.
右转  右转
Right. Right.
向左
Left.
头一夜最难熬  绝对如此
The first night's the toughest. No doubt about it.
光着屁股行进  像刚出生时那样
They march you in naked as the day you were born...
火辣的药粉令你半盲
skin burning and half-blind from that delousing shit.
当你进了囚笼……
And when they put you in that cell...
门闸锁上……
and those bars slam home...
你才明白这是玩真的
that's when you know it's for real.
眨眼间  一生就毁了
Old life blown away in the blink of an eye.
只留下无穷的悔恨
Nothing left but all the time in the world to think about it.
新来的初到之夜多半崩溃
Most new fish come close to madness the first night.
总会有人哭出来
Somebody always breaks down crying.
毫无例外
Happens every time.
唯一的问题是
The only question is...
谁会是第一个
who's it going to be?
用这聚赌也挺有趣的
It's as good a thing to bet on as any, I guess.
我赌安迪·杜弗伦
I had my money on Andy Dufresne.
熄灯
Lights out!
我还记得我来这的第一晚
I remember my first night.
虽然那已经是很久很久以前的事了
Seems like a long time ago.
菜鸟  来嘛
Hey, fish.
菜鸟  菜鸟
Fish, fish.
怎么  怕黑吗？
What are you, scared of the dark?
后悔爸妈搞你出来？
Bet you wish your daddy never dicked your mama!
小猪猪  你的肉好香
Piggy! Pork! I want me a pork chop.
老鸟总是捉弄菜鸟
The boys always go fishing with first-timers.
直到惹哭才罢休
And they don't quit till they reel someone in.
猪公
Hey, Fat Ass.
肥臀
Fat Ass!
说句话嘛
Talk to me, boy.
我听得到你喘气
I know you're there. I can hear you breathing.
别理这些蠢货
Don't you listen to these nitwits, you hear me?
这儿没那么糟啦
This place ain't so bad.
跟你讲
Tell you what...
我会帮你引见  带你过家家
I'll introduce you around, make you feel right at home.
我知道有些个同志
I know a couple of big old bull queers that'd just...
会乐意亲近你
Iove to make your acquaintance.
尤其你那白肉肥臀
Especially that big, white, mushy butt of yours.
天哪
God!
我不要坐牢
I don't belong here!
-有人中奖了  -我要回家
-We have a winner!  -I want to go home!
肥臀中得头名
And it's Fat Ass by a nose!
头名菜鸟！  头名菜鸟！
Fresh fish! Fresh fish!
我不属于这里
I don't belong here
我要回家
I want to go home!
我要见我妈妈
I want my mother!
我搞过你妈  不够爽
I had your mother! She wasn't that great!
天杀的  你们在搞什么鬼？
What the Christ is this horseshit?
你亵渎上帝  我要报告监狱长
He blasphemed. I'll tell the warden.
你菊花插上警棍再去告我吧！
You'll tell him with my baton up your ass!
放我出去！
Let me out!
发什么神经，你这混蛋肥猪
What is your malfunction, you fat barrel of monkey spunk?
求求你！  我本不该在这里！
Please! I ain't supposed to be here.
不该是我！
Not me!
我不想数到三  连一我都不去数
I won't count to three. Not even to one.
马上给我闭嘴  不然就给你来段“催眠曲”
You shut up, or I'll sing you a lullaby!
快闭嘴 不然就完了
Shut up, man. Shut up!
你们弄错了  我不该坐牢的
You don't understand.  I'm not supposed to be here.
开门
Open that cell.
我也不该在这里  这儿被他们搞得像座他妈的监狱！
Me neither! They run this place like a fucking prison!
狗娘养的
Son of a bitch!
长官  别激动
Captain, take it easy!
今晚  再有谁敢哀嚎
If I hear so much as a mouse fart in here tonight...
我就扁得你们全部躺进医务室
I swear by God and Jesus, you will all visit the infirmary.
人人有份
Every last motherfucker in here.
把这废人抬去医务室
Call the trustees. Take that tub of shit down to the infirmary.
安迪头一夜就害我输了两包烟
His first night in the joint, Dufresne cost me two packs of cigarettes.
他一声都没吭
He never made a sound.
北三层  到齐
Tier 3 north, clear count!
南二层  到齐
Tier 2 north, clear count.
南三层  到齐
Tier 3 south, clear.
南一层  到齐
Tier 1 south, clear.
南四层  到齐
Tier 4 south, clear.
准备
Prepare to roll out.
出发
Roll out!
你要吃吗？
Are you going to eat that?
无此打算
I hadn't planned on it.
能给我吗？
Do you mind?
又肥又嫩
That's nice and ripe.
杰克说  谢谢你
Jake says thank you.
它从巢中掉到地上
Fell out of his nest over by the plate shop.
我要养到它会飞
I'm going to look after him until he's big enough to fly.
讨厌  他来了
Oh, no! Here he comes.
早安  伙计们
Morning, fellas.
真是个美好早晨啊
Fine morning, isn't it?
知道为何如此美好吗？
You know why it's a fine morning, don't you?
烟拿出来  就地排好
Send them down. I want them lined up...
像合唱队一样排整齐
just like a pretty little chorus line.
真壮观
Look at that.
-真受不了他  -我的乖乖
-I can't stand this guy.  -Oh, Lord!
没错  正宗吉时香烟
Yes! Richmond, Virginia.
闻我的屁吧
Smell my ass!
闻完再闻我的
After he smells mine.
瑞德  可惜你大大看走眼
That's a shame about your horse coming in last and all.
不过我真感谢我的猪公
But I sure do love that winning horse of mine, though.
出院后我得亲亲他
I owe that boy a big kiss when I see him.
请他抽烟才对  小人得志
Why don't you give him some of your cigarettes instead? Lucky fuck!
嘿  泰瑞
Hey, Tyrell.
这周你在医务室值班吗？
You pull infirmary duty this week?
那肥仔怎样了？
How's my horse doing anyway?
挂了
Dead.
海利打爆了他的头
Hadley busted his head up pretty good.
医生回家睡觉了
Doc had gone home for the night.
他一直僵到天亮
Poor bastard lay there till this morning.
根本无药可救
By then, there wasn't nothing we could do.
他叫什么名字？
What was his name?
你说什么？
What'd you say?
我想知道他的名字
I was just wondering if anyone knew his name.
关你屁事  菜鸟
What the fuck do you care, new fish?
死人还关心什么名字
Doesn't fucking matter what his name was. He's dead.
嘿
Hey
有人上过你了吗？
Anybody come at you yet?
你名草有主了吗？
Anybody get to you yet?
牢里人人需要朋友
Hey, we all need friends in here.
我可以当你朋友
I could be a friend to you.
不易上手
Hard to get.
正合我意
I like that.
起初安迪不与人来往
Andy kept pretty much to himself at first.
大概心事重重
I guess he had a lot on his mind...
努力适应牢狱生活
trying to adapt to life on the inside.
直到一个月后
Wasn't until a month went by before he opened his mouth...
他主动才找人攀谈
to say more than two words to somebody.
那个人……
As it turned out...
就是我
that somebody was me.
我叫安迪·杜弗伦
I'm Andy Dufresne.
杀妻的银行家
Wife-killing banker.
为了什么？
Why'd you do it?
我没犯罪
I didn't, since you ask.
你来对地方了
You're going to fit right in.
这里人人都无罪
Everybody in here's innocent. Didn't you know that?
-赫伍  你为何入狱？  -我无罪  被律师害了
-What you in here for?  -Didn't do it. Lawyer fucked me.
听说你颇爱耍酷
Rumor has it you're a real cold fish.
难道你的屁比别人香？
You think your shit smells sweeter than most. Is that right?
你说呢？
What do you think?
说老实话  我还不清楚
To tell you the truth, I haven't made up my mind.
我知道你很有办法
I understand you're a man that knows how to get things.
我能够让你有求必应
I'm known to locate certain things from time to time.
我想要一把石锤
I wonder if you might get me a rock hammer.
什么？
What?
石锤
A rock hammer.
-用来干什么？  -何必问呢？
-What is it and why?  -What do you care?
若是牙刷  我就直接报价
For a toothbrush, I wouldn't ask. I'd quote a price.
因为牙刷不危险  对吗？
But a toothbrush is a non-lethal object, isn't it?
也有道理
Fair enough.
石锤大约六、七寸长
A rock hammer is about six or seven inches long.
-像鹤嘴锄  -鹤嘴锄？
-Looks like a miniature pickax.  -Pickax?
敲石头用的
For rocks.
石英？
Quartz?
石英
Quartz
云母  页岩……
And some mica, shale...
石灰石
limestone.
所以呢？
So?
我曾是石痴
So I'm a rock hound.
我想重拾往日嗜好
At least I was in my old life. I'd like to be again.
我看你是想捶人家脑袋
Or maybe you'd like to sink your toy into somebody's skull.
不是的  这儿没人犯着我
No, I have no enemies here.
没有？  且慢
No? Wait a while.
话已传开了
Word gets around.
三姐妹对你有性趣
The Sisters have taken quite a liking to you.
尤其是伯格斯
Especially Bogs.
就算跟他们说我不是同性恋也没用吗
Don't suppose it would help if I told them I'm not homosexual.
他们也不是
Neither are they.
同性恋是人  但他们是畜牲
You have to be human first. They don't qualify.
想干就干  根本不在乎你
Bull queers take by force. That's all they want or understand.
我若是你  便会加倍提防
If I were you, I'd grow eyes in the back of my head.
-谢谢你的忠告  -反正不用钱
-Thanks for the advice.  -Well, that's free.
你明白我的顾虑吧
You understand my concern.
我不用石锤惹事  行吗？
If there's trouble, I won't use the rock hammer.
那你想逃狱  挖地道？
Then I'd guess you want to escape. Tunnel under the wall, maybe.
有什么好笑？
What did I miss?  What's so funny?
你看到它就明白了
You'll understand when you see the rock hammer.
它市价多少？
What's an item like this usually go for?
奇石店卖七美元
Seven dollars in any rock-and-gem shop.
我通常加两成
My normal markup's 20 percent.
不过特殊东西嘛
But this is a specialty item.
风险越大  价钱越高  一口价  十美元吧
Risk goes up, price goes up. Let's make it an even 10 bucks.
就这样
Ten it is.
其实你是白花钱
Waste of money, if you ask me.
为什么？
Why's that?
狱方喜欢突击检查
Folks around this joint love surprise inspections.
发现石锤一定没收
They find it, you're going to lose it.
到时候别把我供出来
If they catch you, you don't know me.
否则再也别想跟我做生意
Mention my name, we never do business again.
连口香糖都不卖给你  明白了吗
Not for shoelaces or a stick of gum. Now you got that?
我懂的
I understand.
谢谢  你叫……
Thank you, Mr...
瑞德
Red.
叫我瑞德
Name's Red.
瑞德
Red
为何叫瑞德？
Why do they call you that?
也许因为我是爱尔兰人吧
Maybe it's because I'm Irish.
怪不得有人认为他臭屁
I could see why some of the boys took him for snobby.
他闷声不响
He had a quiet way about him...
步伐和谈吐简直异类
a walk and a talk that just wasn't normal around here.
就像……
He strolled...
在公园散步  无忧无虑
like a man in the park without a care or a worry in the world.
仿佛身披隐形衣
Like he had on an invisible coat that would shield him from this place.
没错
yes
我打一开始
I think it'd be fair to say...
就喜欢他
I liked Andy from the start.
别磨蹭  屁股后还有一大堆事呢
Let's go! Some of us got a schedule to keep.
快点  快点
Move it! Come on, move it!
最近怎样？  你老婆待你还好吗？
How you doing? How's the wife treating you?
继续走
Keep moving.
Just go.
瑞德
Red.
安迪说的对
Andy was right.
见到货我就明白了
I finally got the joke.
用它挖地道
It would take a man about 600 years...
得挖六百年
to tunnel under the wall with one of these.
-要书吗？  -不要
-Book?  -Not today.
-Book? -Not
老布
Brook
给杜弗伦的货
Delivery for Dufresne.
要书吗？
Book?
杜弗伦
Dufresne
你的书
Here's your book.
谢谢
Thanks.
杜弗伦  漂白粉不够了  你去后面拿点
We're running low on hexite. Get on back and fetch us up some.
这东西会弄瞎你的眼
This will blind you.
宝贝  嘘
Honey, hush.
反抗
That's it. You fight!
才刺激
Better that way.
我也希望会是另一种结局
I wish I could tell you Andy fought the good fight...
就是安迪打赢  全身而退
and the Sisters let him be.
我希望如此
I wish I could tell you that...
然而监狱不是童话世界
but prison is no fairy-tale world.
他从没说过是谁干的
He never said who did it.
但谁都明白
But we all knew.
日子就这样一天天过去
Things went on like that for a while.
监狱生活就像例行公事
Prison life consists of routine...
除此之外还是例行公事
and then more routine.
安迪常常挂上新伤
Every so often, Andy would show up with fresh bruises.
三姐妹不放过他
The Sisters kept at him.
他有时打赢
Sometimes he was able to fight them off.
有时吃败仗
Sometimes not.
这就是安迪的监狱生活
And that's how it went for Andy.
这就是他的例行公事
That was his routine.
我相信最初那两年是他最糟糕的
I do believe those first two years were the worst for him.
我也相信日子再这样下去
And I also believe that if things had gone on that way...
这地方早晚会把他毁了
this place would have got the best of him.
但是  在1949年的春天
But then, in the spring of 1949...
上头决定
the powers that be decided:
车牌厂的屋顶需要翻修
The roof of the license-plate factory needs resurfacing.
我需要12名自愿者劳作一周
I need a dozen volunteers for a week's work.
你们都知道
As you know...
特别的公差享有特别的待遇
special detail carries with it special privileges.
这是户外公差
It was outdoor detail...
而五月是户外活动的好时间
and May is one damned fine month to be working outdoors.
排好队
Stay in line there.
一百多人志愿报名
More than a hundred men volunteered for the job.
昂格
Wallace E. Unger.
瑞丁
Ellis Redding.
这不是很巧吗？
Wouldn't you know it?
我的哥们全都中签
Me and some fellows I know were among the names called.
安迪·杜弗伦
Andrew Dufresne.
其实是每人一包烟买的
It only cost us a pack of smokes per man.
我照常抽两成
I made my usual 20 percent, of course.
德州一个律师打电话来
So this big-shot lawyer calls me long-distance from Texas.
我问  “什么事？”
I say, "Yeah?"
他说  “抱歉，令兄过世。”
He says, "Sorry to inform you, but your brother just died."
-我很遗憾  -我才不为那烂人遗憾
-I'm sorry to hear that.  -I'm not. He was an asshole.
他离家多年  早就当他死了
Ran off years ago. Figured him for dead.
这位大律师说
So this lawyer fellow says to me:
“令兄是位富翁。”  挖油井赚了一百万
"He died a rich man." Oil wells and shit. Close to a million bucks.
一百万？
A million bucks?
-对  算他走狗运  -有你一份吗?
-Incredible how lucky some assholes get.  -You going to see any of that?
他留给我三万五
Thirty-five thousand. That's what he left me.
-美金？  -对
Dollars?
简直像中乐透嘛
That's great! That's like winning the sweepstakes.
不是吗？
Isn't it?
政府是白混的吗？
Dumb shit, what do you think the government will do to me?
它想大口分掉这大饼
Take a big wet bite out of my ass is what.
可怜虫
Poor Byron.
过路财神  真够倒霉
Terrible fucking luck, huh? Crying shame.
有人就是命衰
Some people really got it awful.
你疯了？
Andy, are you nuts?
专心干活
IKeep your eyes on your mop, man!
缴了税还剩不少
You'll pay some tax, but you'll still end up...
没错  够换新车
Yeah, maybe enough to buy a new car, and then what?
但买车要缴税
I got to pay tax on the car. Repair...
还要修理  保养  孩子吵着要兜风
maintenance, kids pestering you to take them for a ride all the time.
万一报错税  全得自付
Then if you figure your tax wrong, you pay out of your own pocket.
告诉你  这就是山姆大叔
I tell you! Uncle Sam!
石头都榨得出血来
He puts his hand in your shirt and squeezes your tit till it's purple.
安迪！
Andy! Andy!
-他在找死  -继续干活
-Getting himself killed. -I Keep tarring.
什么哥哥  狗屁！
Some brother. Shit!
海利先生
Mr. Hadley...
你信任老婆吗？
do you trust your wife?
真好笑
Oh, that's funny.
你没了牙给我吹喇叭更好笑
You'll look funnier sucking my dick with no teeth.
她会扯你后腿吗？
What I mean is, do you think she'd go behind your back?
够了  他活得不耐烦了
Step aside, Mert. This fucker's having himself an accident.
他要推落安迪！
He'll push him off!
她要是靠得住
If you trust her, you can keep...
你就能领三万五
that 35,000.
-你说什么？  -三万五
-What did you say?  -Thirty-five thousand.
全部领到
All of it.
-一个子儿也不少  -你最好别耍我
-Every penny.  -You better start making sense.
想领全额  就赠与太太
If you want to keep it,  give it to your wife.
国税局允许一生一次  最多六万的赠与免税
The IRS allows a one-time-only gift to your spouse for up to $ 60,000.
-乖乖  免税？  -对
-Bullshit. Tax-free?  -Tax-free.
国税局征不到一文钱
IRS can't touch one cent.
你是那个杀妻的银行家？
You're that smart banker that killed his wife.
信你难道不会害我坐牢？
Why should I believe you? So I can end up in here with you?
完全合法  你去问国税局也一样
It's legal. Ask the IRS. They'll say the same thing.
我不该开口的  我以为你会去问
I feel stupid telling you this. I'm sure you would have investigated.
我不用你教我这些鸟事
I don't need you to tell me where the bear shit in the buckwheat.
没错  但你要找人填表
Of course not. But you do need someone to set it up for you.
请律师可得花钱
That'll cost you. A lawyer.
没卵的讼棍
A bunch of ball-washing bastards!
我帮你办  给你省钱
I suppose I could set it up for you. That would save you some money.
你领表我来填
You get the forms, I'll prepare them...
完全免费
nearly free of charge.
只要请我同事一人三瓶啤酒
I'd only ask three beers apiece for each of my coworkers.
“同事”？  够新鲜的
"Coworkers." That's rich!
做黑手的有酒喝
A man working outdoors feels more like a man...
才有尊严  这是我的浅见
if he can have a bottle of suds. That's only my opinion...
长官
sir.
看什么看
What are you jimmies staring at?
干活
Let's go! Work!
于是呢
And that's how it came to pass...
在完工前一天
that on the second-to-last day of the job...
49年春的公差犯人
the convict crew that tarred the factory roof in the spring of '49...
早上十点坐成排
wound up sitting in a row at 10:00 in the morning...
喝着冰镇啤酒
drinking icy-cold beer, courtesy of the hardest screw...
肖申克监狱历来最狠的狱官请的客
that ever walked a turn at Shawshank State Prison.
娘儿们  趁凉快喝
Drink up while it's cold, ladies.
这王八蛋还装大方呢
The colossal prick even managed to sound magnanimous.
阳光洒肩头  仿佛自由人
We sat and drank with the sun on our shoulders and felt like free men.
像在修缮自家屋顶
We could have been tarring the roof of one of our own houses.
像是造物主般自在
We were the lords of all creation.
安迪呢……
As for Andy...
他窝在凉荫下
he spent that break hunkered in the shade...
脸上挂着奇异微笑
a strange little smile on his face...
看着我们喝他的酒
watching us drink his beer.
来一瓶吧？
Want a cold one?
谢谢  我戒酒了
No, thanks. I gave up drinking.
你可以说  他想拍狱方马屁
You could argue he done it to curry favor with the guards.
或是想博取狱友交情
Or maybe make a few friends among us cons.
但我呢？
Me?
我认为他只想重温自由
I think he did it just to feel normal again...
哪怕只有一刹那
if only for a short while.
将军
IKing me.
-下棋  是帝王游戏  -什么？
-Chess. Now there's a game of kings. -What?
讲文明  重谋略
Civilized. Strategic.
神秘得要死  真讨厌
And a total fucking mystery. I hate it.
改天我教你吧
Let me teach you someday.
好
Sure.
我想买个棋盘
We could get a board together.
你找对人了  我不论什么都弄得到
You're talking to the right man. I can get things, right?
棋盘用买的  但棋子我来刻
We might do business on a board, and I'll carve the pieces myself.
一半用雪花石膏  一半用皂石
One side in alabaster, one in soapstone. What do you think?
要刻上许多年
I think it'll take years.
时间有的是  就是缺石头
Years I got. What I don't have are the rocks.
操场很贫瘠
Pickings are pretty slim in the yard.
多半是石子
Pebbles, mostly.
咱们算是朋友吧？
We're getting to be kind of friends, aren't we?
算是吧
Yeah, I guess.
能问你个问题吗
Can I ask you something?
你为什么杀人？
Why'd you do it?
我是清白的  瑞德
I'm innocent, Red.
跟大家一样
Just like everybody else here.
你呢？
What are you in for?
跟你一样  杀人
Murder. Same as you.
清白的？
Innocent?
我是肖申克唯一有罪的
Only guilty man in Shawshank.
歌女呢？
Where's the canary?
你怎么知道？
How did you know?
-我知道什么？  -原来你不知道
-How did I know what?  -So you don't know.
来
Come.
歌女在这里
This is where the canary is.
没想到她来寒舍献唱吧
Quite a surprise to hear a woman singing in my house, eh?
的确……
That's quite a...
没想到
surprise.
瑞德
Red
等一下
Wait, wait.
她要上场了
Here she comes.
我最迷她甩头发的骚样
I like this part when she does that shit with her hair.
这个月看过三场了
I know. I've seen it three times this month.
姬旦  你衣着整齐吗？
Gilda, are you decent?
在说我？
Me?
我爱死这段了
God, I love it.
听说阁下有求必应
I understand you're a man that knows how to get things.
在下确非浪得虚名  你要什么？
I'm known to locate certain things from time to time. What do you want?
-丽塔·海华丝  -什么？
-Rita Hayworth. -What?
弄得到吗？
Can you get her?
这位就是约翰尼·法雷尔啊  久仰久仰
So this is Johnny Farrel. I've heard a lot about you.
-要几个星期  -几星期？
-Take a few weeks. -Weeks?
我又没把她压在下面  抱歉这么说
I don't have her stuffed down the front of my pants right now, sorry to say.
沉住气哦  法雷尔先生
反正弄得到
But I'll get her.
放心
Relax.
谢了
Thanks.
的确  你该见见他
说了我来做什么吗？
不  我要让他惊喜
-出去  -我得放映
-Get out!  -I got to change reels!
我叫你滚
I said fuck off!
你不尖叫吗？
Ain't you going to scream?
咱们算算总帐
Let's get this over with.
他打破我鼻子
He broke my fucking nose!
现在
Now...
我要解拉链
I'm going to open my fly...
叫你含什么你就含
and you'll swallow what I give you to swallow.
先舔我  再舔公鸡  因为你害他流鼻血
Then you'll swallow Rooster's.  You broke his nose.
他应该得到偿还
He ought to have something to show for it.
它进我的嘴  就跟你分家
You put it in my mouth, you lose it.
不  你没搞懂
No, you don't understand.
我会用钻子刺穿你耳朵
Do that and I'll put all eight inches of this in your ear.
那你知道吗  脑部遇袭
All right, but you should know that sudden, serious brain injury...
会使人死劲咬
causes the victim to bite down hard.
用力之大
In fact, I hear the bite reflex is so strong...
得用撬棍
they have to pry the victim's jaws open...
才扳得开
with a crowbar.
你怎么知道？
Where do you get this shit?
书上写的
I read it.
你识字吗  豆腐脑？
You know how to read, you ignorant fuck?
亲爱的
Honey!
你不该损我
You shouldn't!
伯格斯没逼他吹喇叭
Bogs didn't put anything in Andy's mouth.
其他两个也不敢
And neither did his friends.
他们把安迪打个半死
What they did do is beat him within an inch of his life.
在医务室里待了一个月
Andy spent a month in the infirmary.
伯格斯被关禁闭一周
Bogs spent a week in the hole.
时间到
Time's up, Bogs.
遵命  头儿
It's your world, boss.
回牢房准备点名
Return to your cellblocks for evening count.
全部回牢房
All prisoners report for lock down.
什么事？
What?
-他想去哪儿？  -抓住脚
-Where's he going?  -Grab his ankles.
不要……救命！
No...help!
此后  有两件事再也没发生过
Two things never happened again after that.
三姐妹再也没碰安迪
The Sisters never laid a finger on Andy again.
伯格斯再也无法走路
And Bogs would never walk again.
他被转送到低戒护的医院
They transferred him to a minimum-security hospital upstate.
我只知道他的余生
To my knowledge, he lived out the rest of his days...
全靠吸管进食
drinking his food through a straw.
我想热烈欢迎安迪出院
Andy could use a nice welcome back when he gets out of the infirmary.
没问题
Sounds good to us.
咱们欠他的酒
I figure we owe him that much for the beer.
他喜欢下棋
The man likes to play chess.
帮他找石头吧
Let's get him some rocks.
各位！
Guys!
我找到一块
I got one.
快瞧！
I got one. Look!
那不是皂石 也不是雪花石
Heywood, that isn't soapstone! And it ain't alabaster either.
你他妈是地质学家？
What are you, a fucking geologist?
他说的没错
He's right. It ain't.
-那这是什么？  -马粪蛋
-What the hell is it then? -It's a horse apple.
-胡说!  -没有  就是马粪
-Bullshit!  -No, horseshit.
马粪化石
Petrified.
天哪
God!
他妈的
Damn!
错误难免  但众志成城
Despite a few hitches, the boys came through in fine style.
在安迪出院前一周
And by the weekend he was due back...
石头多得够他刻一辈子
we had enough rocks saved up to keep him busy till rapture.
同时到了一大批货
Also got a big shipment in that week.
烟
Cigarettes...
口香糖
chewing gum...
威士忌
sipping whisky...
裸女扑克牌
playing cards with naked ladies on them. You name it.
当然  最重要的当属
And of course, the most important item:
丽塔·海华丝
Rita Hayworth herself.
醒醒
Wake up
小心  来搜查了
Heads up. They're tossing cells.
Heads up. They're tossing cells!
119.
123.
站起来
On your feet.
面对墙
Face the wall.
转身面向典狱长
Turn around and face the warden.
很高兴你在看圣经
Pleased to see you reading this.
你最喜欢哪一章节？
Any favorite passages?
“所以你们要惊醒，”
"Watch ye, therefore,for ye know not...
“因为不知道家主何时到来。”
when the master of the house cometh."
马可福音  13章35节
Mark 13:35.
我也一向喜欢它
I've always liked that one.
但我更偏爱——
But I prefer...
“我是世界的光，”
"I am the light of the world.
“跟从我的，就不会走进黑暗，必要得跟着生命的光。”
Ye that followeth me shall have the light of life."
约翰福音  8章12节
John, chapter 8, verse 12.
听说你精通数字
I hear you're good with numbers.
很好
How nice.
人应该有专长
Man should have a skill.
这是什么？
Explain this.
磨石毡  打磨石头用的
It's called a rock blanket. It's for shaping and polishing rocks.
我的小嗜好
A little hobby of mine.
很标准
It's pretty clean.
无重大违规
Some contraband here, but nothing to get in a twist over.
这个嘛  我不大赞成
I can't say I approve of this.
不过嘛……
But I suppose...
破个例也无妨
exceptions can be made.
锁门
Lock them up!
差点忘了
I almost forgot.
我怎能拿你的圣经
I'd hate to deprive you of this.
“救赎之道，就在其中。”
Salvation lies within.
是的  先生
Yes, sir.
搜查只是借口
Tossing cells was just an excuse.
事实是……
Truth is...
诺顿要秤他斤两
Norton wanted to size Andy up.
我太太在教堂织的
My wife made that in church group.
相当精巧
Very nice, sir.
喜欢洗衣房的工作吗？
You enjoy working the laundry?
不怎么喜欢
No, sir. Not especially.
也许我们可以换个别的……
Perhaps we can find something more...
让你发挥才学
befitting a man of your education.
杰克  老布人呢？
Hey, Jake. Where's Brooks?
安迪  我听见你来了
I thought I heard you out here.
我转派给你
I've been reassigned to you.
我听说了
I know, they told me.
真想不到
Ain't that a kick in the head?
来个小小巡礼吧
Well, I'll give you the dime tour.
来吧
Come on.
都在你眼前了
Well, here she is.
肖申克监狱图书馆
The Shawshank Prison Library.
国家地理杂志
National Geographics...
读者文摘
Reader's Digest condensed books...
畅销西部小说
and Louis L'Amour.
展望杂志
Look magazine.
悬疑小说
Erle Stanley Gardners.
每晚搬上车兜一圈
Every evening I load up the cart and make my rounds.
记下借书人名字
I enter the names on this clipboard here.
如此往复  简简单单
Easy, peasy, Japanese-y.
-有问题吗？  -你管图书馆多久了?
-Any questions?  -How long have you been librarian?
1905年入狱  1912年入馆
I come here in '05, and they made me librarian in 1912.
这么多年都没有助手？
And have you ever had an assistant?
没有  根本用不着
No. Not much to it, really.
那为何派我来？
Why me? Why now?
不知道
I don't know.
但有人作伴真好
But it'd be nice to have some company down here.
杜弗伦
Dufresne
就是他
That's him. That's the one.
我是狄金斯
I'm Dekins.
我在想……
I was thinking...
为孩子弄个教育基金
about setting up some kind of trust fund for my kids' educations.
我懂了
I see.
咱们坐下谈吧
Why don't we have a seat and talk it over.
老布  有纸笔吗？
Do you have a piece of paper and a pencil?
谢谢
Thanks.
那么
So...
狄金斯先生
Mister Dekins...
然后安迪说
And then Andy says, "Mr. Dekins...
“你想让贵公子进哈佛还是耶鲁？”
do you want your sons to go to Harvard or Yale?"
你少瞎扯
He didn't say that!
真的  老天为证
As God as my witness!
他愣了一下
Dekins blinked for a second...
傻笑出来  后来真跟安迪握手了
then he laughed and actually shook Andy's hand.
-握你的鸟  -真的握手
-My ass!  -Shook his hand.
我乐的差点尿出来
I tell you, I near soiled myself!
若给安迪弄一套西装领带
All he needed was a suit and tie and a jiggly hula gal on his desk...
他就成了“咨询先生”
he'd have been "Mr. Dufresne," if you please.
开始交新朋友了  安迪？
Making a few friends?
也不算“朋友”
I wouldn't say "friends."
我是精通理财的囚徒
I'm a convicted murderer who provides sound financial planning.
这种本事很受用
It's a wonderful pet to have.
起码不用干洗衣工
Got you out of the laundry, though.
还派得上更大用场
It might do more than that.
比如扩建图书馆  买新书
How about expanding the library. Get some new books.
还不如申请张台球桌
If you ask for something, ask for a pool table.
对
yes.
你想怎么弄？
How do you expect to do that? I mean...
我是说  “咨询先生”  你打算怎么弄到新书？
get new books in here, "Mr. Dufresne, if you please."
找典狱长要钱
I'll ask the warden for funds.
孩子  我经历了六任典狱长
Son, son, son... Six wardens have been through here in my tenure, and I've learned...
学到的互古不变的真理就是
one immutable, universal truth:
给钱是不可能的
Not one born whose asshole...
他们没一个生来有屁眼
wouldn't pucker up tighter than a snare drum when you ask for funds.
-预算太少了  -我了解
-The budget's stretched thin as it is.  -I see.
我可以写信跟州议会要钱
Maybe I could write the state senate and request funds from them.
监狱领到款只能做三种用途
They have only three ways to spend the taxpayers' money for prisons:
筑高墙  加牢笼  添警卫
More walls, more bars, more guards.
我仍请您恩准  一周一信
I'd like to try, with permission. A letter a week.
-总会有结果  -难说哦
-They can't ignore me forever.  -Sure can.
想写就写吧
But you write your letters if it makes you happy.
我一定寄出  行吗？
I'll even mail them for you. How's that?
安迪开始一周一信
So Andy started writing a letter a week...
他说话算话
just like he said.
不过  就像诺顿说的
And like Norton said...
毫无回音
Andy got no answers.
次年  他替半数的警卫报税
The following April, he did tax returns for half the guards at Shawshank.
再过一年  全都找他帮忙
Year after that, he did them all...
包括典狱长的
including the warden's.
再过一年  狱际棒球赛
Year after that, they rescheduled the intramural season...
改在与税季重叠
to coincide with tax season.
各监狱的警卫都带税单找他
The guards on the opposing teams all remembered to bring their W-2s.
狱方发枪给你
So Moresby Prison...
但要你付钱
issued you a gun, but you paid for it.
连枪套也要我付
Right. The holster too.
这笔钱可以扣除
That's tax-deductible. You can write that off.
没错  安迪就像开小作坊
Yes, sir! Andy was a regular cottage industry.
税季繁忙时  还可请帮手
In fact, it got so busy at tax time, he was allowed a staff.
请帮我拿一叠表格
Could you hand me a stack of 1040s?
每年此时我调离工厂  乐到心坎里
Got me out of the wood shop a month out of the year, and that was fine by me.
至于信  他仍继续寄
And still, he kept sending those letters.
瑞德  安迪  老布出事了
It's Brooks.
守着门
Watch the door.
冷静点  老布
Please, Brooks.
-冲动个啥  -混帐  退后
-Calm the fuck down.  -Stay back!
-都退后  -怎么回事？
-Stay back, goddamn it!  -What's going on?
上一秒好好的  突然亮刀子
One second he's fine, then out come the knives.
老布  有话好说
We can talk about this, right?
放屁  没啥可说  我要割断他喉咙
There's nothing to talk about. I'll cut his fucking throat.
等一下  赫伍哪里不对？
What's he done to you?
错在他们
It's what they done!
我别无选择
I got no choice.
谁都知道你不会伤害他
You won't hurt Heywood. We all know that.
-对  是吧赫伍？  -没错
-Right, Heywood?  -Sure.
因为他是朋友  而你明理
He's a friend of yours, and Brooks is a reasonable man.
-对不对？
Right, guys?
老布  看着我  放下刀
So put the knife down. Look at me.
把刀放下
Put the knife down.
老布  你瞧他的脖子
Look at his neck, for God's sake.
看看  都流血了
Look at his neck. He's bleeding.
只有闯祸……
It's the only way...
才能留在牢里
they'd let me stay.
怎么可能  别做傻事
This is crazy. You don't want to do this.
把刀放下
Put it, put it down.
放松点
Take it easy.
不会有事的
You'll be all right.
他没事  我呢？
Him? What about me?
老疯狗差点割断我喉咙
Crazy old fool damn near cut my throat!
你刮胡子不也刀刀见血
You've had worse from shaving.
你怎么惹毛他的？
What did you do to set him off?
哪有  我只是来道别
Nothing. I come in here to say farewell.
上面准他假释了
Ain't you heard? His parole's come through.
我实在搞不明白
I just don't understand what happened in there.
这老家伙简直疯了
Old man's crazy as a rat in a tin shithouse.
赫伍  住口
That's enough out of you.
-听说你吓的屁滚尿流  -滚你的
-Heard he had you shitting your pants. -Fuck you.
别斗嘴了
Knock it off.
老布没疯
Brooks ain't no bug.
他只是……
he is just...
体制化了
institutionalized.
“体制化”？  什么鸟词儿
"Institutionalized," my ass.
他坐了50年的牢  赫伍  50年呀
The man's been in here 50 years, Heywood, 50 years!
成了井底之蛙
This is all he knows.
他念过书
In here, he's an important man...
在狱中有地位
an educated man.
出狱就成了废人
Outside, he's nothing.
双手犯关节炎的囚徒
Just a used-up con with arthritis in both hands.
想向图书馆借书都会被拒
Probably couldn't get a library card if he tried.
这样说你懂吗？
You know what I'm trying to say?
我才不懂你的满嘴屁话
I do believe you're talking out of your ass.
随你怎么想吧
You believe whatever you want.
监狱是怪地方
But I tell you these walls are funny.
起先你恨它
First you hate them.
然后习惯它
Then you get used to them.
更久后
Enough time passes...
你离不开它
you get so you depend on them.
这就叫“体制化”
That's "institutionalized."
狗屎
Shit.
-我才不会呢  -是吗？
-I could never get like that. -Oh, yeah?
等你呆到老布那把年纪 你就知道了
Wait till you've been here as long as Brooks.
说的太对了
Goddamn right.
他们把你送到这里来度日
They send you here for life...
等于拿走你一生的年华
that's exactly what they take.
至少是一大部分
Part that counts, anyway.
杰克  我无法再照顾你
I can't take care of you no more, Jake.
走吧  你自由了
You go on now.
自由了
You're free.
一切顺利  老布
Good luck, Brooksie.
保重
“亲爱的牢友：”
Dear fellas:
“外头的变化快得难以置信。”
I can't believe how fast things move on the outside.
老头儿  嫌命长吗
Watch it, old-timer! Want to get killed?
“小时候我只看过一辆汽车，”
I saw an automobile once when I was a kid...
“如今满街都是，”
but now they're everywhere.
“整个世界忙成一团。”
The world went and got itself in a big damn hurry.
“上面安排我”
The parole board got me into this halfway house...
“到‘中途之家’，”
called "The Brewer"...
“并在超市”
and a job...
“当包装员。”
bagging groceries at the Food-Way.
“工作辛苦，我也卖力，”
It's hard work and I try to keep up...
“但双手一直犯疼。”
..but my hands hurt most of the time.
叫他务必用双层袋
Make sure your man double-bags.
上次差点撑破袋子
Last time, the bottom near came out.
确定要用双层袋
Make sure you double-bag like the lady says. understand?
是  没问题
Yes, sir. Surely will.
“店长不怎么喜欢我。”
I don't think the store manager likes me very much.
“工作之余我去公园喂鸟，”
Sometimes after work, I go to the park and feed the birds.
“盼望……”
I keep thinking...
“杰克来打个招呼，”
Jake might just show up and say hello.
“但它没出现过。”
But he never does.
“不管它在何处，我祝它过的好、有新朋友。”
I hope, wherever he is, he's doing okay and making new friends.
“我夜间难以入眠，”
I have trouble sleeping at night.
“做着从高处坠落的噩梦。”
I have bad dreams like I'm falling.
“从梦中惊醒，”
I wake up scared.
“有时记不起身在何方。”
Sometimes it takes me a while to remember where I am.
“也许我该持枪抢劫，好让他们送我回去。”
Maybe I should get a gun and rob the Food-Way so they'd send me home.
“我可以打死那个店长，当作额外奖励。”
I could shoot the manager while I was at it. Sort of like a bonus.
“但我老的无法再胡闹了。”
I guess I'm too old for that sort of nonsense anymore.
“我不喜欢这里，”
I don't like it here.
“我厌倦成天担惊受怕。”
I'm tired of being afraid all the time. I've decided...
“于是，我决心不再逗留。”
not to stay.
“当局不会在乎我，”
I doubt they'll kick up any fuss...
“一个糟老头算什么。”
not for an old crook like me.
“当局不会在乎我，一个糟老头算什么。”
"I doubt they'll kick up any fuss, not for an old crook like me.
“还有，替我向赫伍道歉，”
P.S. Tell Heywood I'm sorry I put a knife to his throat.
“别记恨在心。你们的老布”
No hard feelings. Brooks."
他还不如老死在肖申克好
He should have died in here.
瞧瞧你干的好事
What the fuck have you done?
一片混乱
It's a goddamn mess, I'll tell you that.
-这些是什么？  -你说呢  全是寄给你的
-What's all this?  -You tell me. They're addressed to you.
看下这个
Take it.
“杜弗伦先生：”
"Dear Mr. Dufresne:
“鉴于你再三询问，”
In response to your inquiries...
“本州特拨款给贵图书馆。”
the state has allocated the enclosed funds for your library project."
有两百元
This is $ 200.
“另外，主管单位”
"In addition, the library district has generously responded...
“特地捐赠旧书及杂物，”
with a donation of used books and sundries.
“相信可满足阁下需要，就此了结，”
We trust this will fill your needs. We now consider the matter closed.
“勿再来信。”
Please stop sending us letters."
典狱长回来前清理干净
Clear all this out before the warden gets back.
是
Yes, sir.
干的好  安迪
Good for you, Andy.
哇！
Wow!
只写了六年
It only took six years.
现在起我一周两封
From now on, I'll write two letters a week instead of one.
你真够固执的  听队长的话
I believe you're crazy enough.  Get this stuff out...
把东西清干净  我去解大便
like he said. I've got to pinch a loaf.
别让我出来
When I come back...
再看到这些
this is all gone, all right?
安迪  什么声音？
Do you hear that?
杜弗伦
Dufresne!
安迪  放我出去！
Andy, let me out!
安迪！
Andy!
到现在我还搞不懂她们唱什么
I have no idea to this day what those two Italian ladies were singing about.
其实我也不想弄懂
Truth is, I don't want to know.
此时无言胜有言
Some things are best left unsaid.
她们唱出
I like to think it was something so beautiful...
难以言传的美
it can't be expressed in words...
美得令你心碎
and makes your heart ache because of it.
歌声直窜云端
I tell you, those voices soared...
超越失意囚徒的梦想
higher and farther than anybody in a gray place dares to dream.
宛如小鸟飞入牢房
It was like a beautiful bird flapped into our drab cage...
使石墙消失无踪
and made those walls dissolve away.
就在这一瞬间
And for the briefest of moments...
肖申克众囚仿佛重获自由
every last man at Shawshank felt free.
典狱长可发飚了
It pissed the warden off something awful.
开门
Open the door.
Open it up!
杜弗伦  开门
Dufresne, open this door!
关掉
Turn that off!
我警告你  关掉
I am warning you. Turn that off!
杜弗伦
Dufresne!
敬酒不吃吃罚酒
You're mine now.
安迪被关禁闭两周
Andy got two weeks in the hole for that little stunt.
站起来
On your feet.
-看谁来了  -大指挥家
-Hey, look who's here.  -Maestro!
你没别的可放吗？  比如汉克·威廉斯的歌？
You couldn't play something good, huh? Like Hank Williams?
没等接受点歌  他们就破门而入了
They broke the door down before I could take requests.
-关两周值得吗？  -我最舒服的两周
-Was it worth two weeks?  -Easiest time I ever did.
-屁话  关小号最难熬了  -在里面度日如年
-No such thing as easy time in the hole. -A week in the hole is like a year.
-半点不假  -有莫札特陪我
-Damn straight.  -I had Mr. Mozart to keep me company.
他们准你带留声机？
So they let you tote that record player down there, huh?
在脑中
It was in here.
在心底
In here.
音乐之美
That's the beauty of music.
是夺不走的
They can't get that from you.
你没体会过吗？
Haven't you ever felt that way about music?
我年轻时吹过口琴
Well, I played a mean harmonica as a younger man.
后来没兴致了
Lost interest in it, though.
在牢里也没意义
Didn't make much sense in here.
就是在这里才有意义
Here's where it makes the most sense.
有音乐才不会忘记
You need it so you don't forget.
忘记什么？
Forget?
世上
Forget that there are...
有些地方
places...
是石墙围不住的
in the world that aren't made out of stone.
在人的
There's something...
内心深处
inside...
有他们找不到
that they can't get to...
拿不走的东西
that they can't touch.
完全属于你自己的东西
That's yours.
你指什么？
What are you talking about?
希望
Hope.
朋友  我告诉你
Let me tell you something, my friend.
有希望才危险
Hope is a dangerous thing.
希望能把人逼疯
Hope can drive a man insane.
在这里  希望毫无用处
It's got no use on the inside.
你最好认命
You'd better get used to that idea.
要像老布一样吗？
Like Brooks did?
坐下
Sit down.
根据你的材料 你的终身监禁已经服满30年
Says here that you've served 30 years of a life sentence.
你改过自新了吗？
You feel you've been rehabilitated?
是的
Oh, yes, sir.
我真的已经变好了
Without a doubt.
我完全洗心革面了
I can honestly say I'm a changed man.
我不会再危害社会
No danger to society here.
我向上帝发誓
God's honest truth.
我绝对改过自新了
Absolutely rehabilitated.
30年了
Thirty years.
老天  真不知该说什么？
Jesus, when you say it like that...
这些日子怎么熬过来的
You wonder where it went.
我连前十年都不记得了
I wonder where 10 years went.
拿去
Here.
假释被拒的礼物
A little parole rejection present.
打开看看
Go ahead and open it.
别介意我找你同行买
Went through one of your competitors.
我只想给你一个惊喜
I hope you don't mind. I wanted it to be a surprise.
漂亮极了
It's very pretty.
谢谢
Thank you.
你不吹吗？
You going to play it?
不
No.
不是时候
Not right now.
进牢
Roll in!
熄灯
Lights out!
安迪言出必行
Andy was as good as his word.
每周写两封信
He wrote two letters a week instead of one.
59年  州议会终于明白
In 1959, the state senate finally clued in to the fact...
两百元无法打发安迪
they couldn't buy him off with just a $ 200 check.
当局决定每年拨款五百美元
Appropriations Committee voted an annual payment of $500...
好让安迪封笔
just to shut him up.
你想像不到他的能耐
And you'd be amazed how far Andy could stretch it.
他接洽读书会  慈善团体
He made deals with book clubs, charity groups.
他论斤买入旧书
He bought remaindered books by the pound...
《金银岛》
"Treasure Island".
罗伯特·路易斯
Robert Louis...
史蒂文森
Stevenson.
冒险小说类
Fiction, adventure.
下一本
What's next?
汽车维修
I got here Auto Repair...
肥皂雕刻
and Soap Carving.
专业技术及嗜好  教育类  在你后面
Trade skills and hobbies. Under "Educational," behind you.
基堵山恩仇记
Count of Monte Crisco.
基督山  饭桶
That's "Cristo," you dumb shit.
作者亚历山大……
By Alexandree...
大种马
Dum-ass.
种马？
Dumb ass.
Dumb ass?
大仲马  内容知道吗？
Dumas. Know what that's about?
讲逃狱  你会喜欢的
You'd like it. It's about a prison break.
那该归入教育类啰
We ought to file that under "Educational" too, oughtn't we?
大伙儿尽可能地帮忙
The rest of us did our best to pitch in when and where we could.
在肯尼迪遇刺那年
By the year Kennedy was shot...
安迪把这间臭储藏室变成
Andy had transformed a storage room smelling of turpentine...
新英格兰最棒的监狱图书馆
into the best prison library in New England...
甚至有汉克·威廉斯精选集
complete with a fine selection of Hank Williams.
就在同年
That was also when Warden Norton...
典狱长实施著名的“外役”专案
instituted his famous "Inside Out" program.
也许你曾在报上看过
You may remember reading about it.
他上了各报和《展望杂志》
It made the papers and got his picture in Look magazine.
这不是放任自由
It's no free ride...
而是狱政的
but rather a genuine progressive advance...
一大进步
in corrections and rehabilitation.
本监获刑人在妥善监督下
Our inmates, properly supervised...
将到狱外劳动
will be put to work outside these walls...
从事各项公共事业
performing all manner of public service.
他们将学到诚实劳动的价值
These men can learn the value...
同时为社区提供服务
of an honest day's labor and provide a service to the community...
对于纳税大众而言  也只花最少的代价
at a bare minimum of expense to Mr. And Mrs. John Q. Taxpayer.
当然  诺顿没向媒体说明
Of course he didn't tell the press...
“最少代价”实在含糊不清
that "bare minimum of expense" is a fairly loose term.
揩油的方法何止百种
There are 100 different ways to skim off the top.
人力  物料  处处漏洞
Men, materials, you name it.
天哪  油水超多
And oh, my Lord, how the money rolled in!
你会害我倒闭的
At this rate, you'll put me out of business.
靠这么多奴工  谁投标投得过你
With this pool of slave labor, you can underbid any contractor in town.
我们在提供社区服务
We're providing a valuable community service.
这是说词  我得养家
That's fine for the papers, but I've got a family to feed.
老兄  咱们这么久的交情
We go back a long way.
我需要包下这条公路  不然只好喝西北风了
I need this highway contract. I don't get it and I go under. That's a fact.
这是我太太特地为你烤的派
You have some of this fine pie...
请笑纳
my missus made for you. You think about that.
别担心这项工程合约
I wouldn't worry too much about this contract.
我已叫他们接别的项目了
I already got my boys committed elsewhere.
帮我谢谢她的心意
You be sure and thank Maisie for this fine pie.
在每一桩买卖背后
And behind every shady deal...
在每一个黑钱底下
behind every dollar earned...
都有安迪在  是他做的帐
there was Andy, keeping the books.
有两笔要存入银行
Two deposits.
照旧在夜间  存到缅因国际和新英格兰
Maine National and New England First. Night drops as always, sir.
把东西拿去洗衣房  两套西装和杂物
Get my stuff to the laundry. Two suits for dry-clean and a bag of whatnot.
-别浆太硬  否则有他们好看  -是  先生
If they over-starch my shirts again, they'll hear from me.
我怎样？
How do I look?
-很好  先生  -要去参加盛大的慈善宴会
-Very nice.  -Big charity to-do up Portland way.
州长会到
Governor will be there.
剩下的给你吃
You want the rest of this?
烤的难吃透顶
Woman can't bake worth shit.
谢谢您  先生
Thank you, sir.
我听说这种派他收过很多
He's got his fingers in a lot of pies, from what I hear.
你听说的只是皮毛  他干的坏事你根本想不到  重重的回扣
He's got scams you haven't even dreamed of. Kickbacks on his kickbacks.
黑钱如河般在他脚下流
A river of dirty money running through here.
贪污这么多迟早会曝光
Sooner or later, he'll have to explain where it came from.
因此才要用我
That's where I come in.
我过滤黑钱  一一漂白
I channel it. Filter it. Funnel it.
股票  证券  市政公债
Stocks, securities, tax-free municipals.
我让脏钱流入市场  等它回流时……
I send it out into the real world, and when it comes back...
-干净的像处女？  -比那更干净
-Clean as a virgin's honeypot, huh?  -Cleaner.
诺顿退休时  将是百万富翁
By the time Norton retires, I'll have made him a millionaire.
若被逮到  他也会被关入肖申克
If they ever catch on, he'll wind up in here wearing a number himself.
你对我这么没信心啊
I thought you had more faith in me than that.
我知道你很能干  但总会有蛛丝马迹留下
I know you're good, but all that paper leaves a trail.
万一调查局或国税局起疑
Now anybody gets curious, FBI, IRS...
就完了
whatever.
总有人要遭殃
It'll lead to somebody.
没错  但不是我  更不是典狱长
Sure it is, but not to me, and certainly not to the warden.
那是谁？
All right, who?
兰道·史帝文
Randall Stevens.
谁？
Who?
隐名又隐形的合伙人
The "silent" silent partner.
法官  要怪怪他  户头是他的
He's the guilty one, the man with the bank accounts.
他是洗钱的起点
It's where the filtering process starts.
出了差错  只追得到他
They trace anything, it'll just lead to him.
但他是什么人？
But who is he?
他是幻影  幽灵  兔子哈维的远房表亲
He's a phantom, an apparition. Second cousin to Harvey the Rabbit.
他由我一手
I conjured him...
凭空塑造
out of thin air.
他不存在  除了在文件上
He doesn't exist, except on paper.
哪有凭空造人的？
You can't just make a person up.
利用制度的漏洞就行
Sure you can, if you know how the system works.
靠写信能办成太多的事
It's amazing what you can accomplish by mail.
史帝文有出生证明
Mr. Stevens has a birth certificate...
有驾照  社会保险编号
driver's license, Social Security.
你在逗我吧？
You're shitting me.
就算抓到蛛丝马迹
If they trace any accounts, they'll wind up chasing...
也等于捕风捉影
a figment of my imagination.
真想不到
Well, I'll be damned!
我有称赞过你吧？
Did I say you were good?
你简直是大艺术家
Shit, you are Rembrandt.
可笑的是
The funny thing is...
在外头  我刚正不阿
on the outside, I was an honest man, straight as an arrow.
进了牢  却大搞欺骗
I had to come to prison to be a crook.
你担心过吗？
Ever bother you?
我没干坏事  只是洗钱
I don't run the scams. I just process the profits.
也许这是强词夺理
A fine line, maybe...
但我建起图书馆
but I also built that library...
帮助囚友考取高中文凭
and used it to help guys get their high school diploma.
典狱长凭什么放任不管？
Why do you think he lets me do all that?
为了使你
IKeep you happy and doing the laundry.
乐于帮他洗钱
Money instead of sheets.
我算是便宜卖给他
Well, I work cheap. That's the tradeoff.
汤米在65年来到肖申克
Tommy Williams came to Shawshank in 1965...
犯了“入室行窃”  判了两年
on a two-year stretch for B and E.
就是强行侵入他人公宅
That's breaking and entering to you.
他在商店后门偷彩电时被逮
Cops caught him sneaking TV sets out the back door of a JC Penney.
小朋克
Young punk.
摇滚狂一个
Mr. Rock 'n' Roll...
跩得够可爱
cocky as hell.
快点 老家伙们 慢得跟糖浆一样
Come on, old boys. Moving like molasses!
我看了难过
Making me look bad.
人见人爱
We liked him immediately.
我退出门外  就这样抱着电视
I'm backing out the door and I got the TV like this.
它很大  害我看不见  忽然传来
A big old thing. I couldn't see shit. Then I hear this voice.
“别动，举起手来！”
"Freeze, kid, hands in the air."
我站着抱紧电视
I was standing there, holding onto that TV. Finally the voice says:
他又说  “你听到没有？”  我说  “听到，但我若松手，”
"You hear what I said, boy?" I say, "Yes, sir. I did.
“就要添一条毁坏财产罪。”
But if I drop this, you get me on destruction of property too."
你在凯希曼监狱蹲过？
You done some stretch in Cashman, right?
那儿要好过得多
Yeah, that was an easy piece of time, let me tell you.
周末回家  活也轻松
Weekend furloughs. Work programs.
不像这里
Not like here.
你哪里都蹲过嘛
Sounds like you done time all over.
我13岁起以牢为家
I've been in and out since I was 13.
你叫得上名的监狱我都待过
Name it, chances are I've been there.
也许你该改行了
Perhaps you should try a new profession.
依我看
What I mean is...
你的贼功不灵光  该做做别的事
you're not a very good thief.You should try something else.
你懂个屁  你是卡彭？
Yeah, what the hell you know about it, Capone?
你因何入狱？
What are you in for?
我？
Me?
被律师害了
A lawyer fucked me.
肖申克没人有罪  你不知道？
Everybody's innocent in here. Don't you know that?
汤米有娇妻和刚出生的女儿
As it turned out, Tommy had himself a young wife and a new baby girl.
他怕妻女流落街头
Maybe he thought of them on the streets...
到头来不认识老爸
or his child growing up not knowing her daddy.
或是别的什么原因
Whatever it was...
反正这小子卯上了
something lit a fire under that boy's ass.
我想考高中文凭
Thought I might try for my high school equivalency.
听说你帮过人
Hear you helped a couple of fellas with that.
我不帮废柴
I don't waste time with losers, Tommy.
我才不是废柴
I ain't no goddamn loser.
-你当真？  -对
-You mean that?  -Yeah.
真的当真？
You really mean that?
真的
Yes, sir, I do.
好  要冲就冲到底
Good. Because if we do this...
百分之百努力  不可半途而废
we do it all the way, a hundred percent, nothing half-assed.
问题是……
Thing is, see...
我不太识字
I don't read so good.
好吧
Well.
你不太识字……
You don't read...
没关系
so well.
交给我吧
We'll get to that.
安迪收汤米为徒
So, Andy took Tommy under his wing.
从字母教起
Started walking him through his ABC's.
汤米学得非常好
Tommy took to it pretty well too.
他从未发现自己有天份
Boy found brains he never knew he had.
没多久就开始准备考试
Before long, Andy started him on his course requirements.
安迪真心喜欢他
He really liked the kid.
助人向上令他兴奋
Gave him a thrill to help a youngster crawl off the shit heap.
但动机不止于此
But that wasn't the only reason.
牢狱生活漫长得很
Prison time is slow time.
必须找事打发时间
So you do what you can to keep going.
有人集邮
Some fellas collect stamps.
有人盖火柴屋
Others build matchstick houses.
安迪成立了图书馆
Andy built a library.
如今他需要新事由
Now he needed a new project.
那就是汤米
Tommy was it.
这跟他长年刻石一样
It was the same reason he spent years shaping and polishing those rocks.
也跟他挂美女图一样
The same reason he hung his fantasy girlies on the wall.
在牢里
In prison...
没事也得找事做
a man will do most anything to keep his mind occupied.
1966年  就在汤米应考之前
By 1966, right about the time Tommy was getting ready to take his exams...
换上拉寇儿·薇芝了
it was lovely Raquel.
时间到
Time.
怎样？
Well?
烂透了
Well, it's for shit.
我他妈白费一整年
I wasted a whole year of my time with this bullshit.
也许没那么糟
It's probably not that bad.
就没一道题做对  简直像看中文
I didn't get a thing right. It might as well have been in Chinese.
分数出来再说
Let's see how the score comes out.
我告诉你几分吧
I'll tell you how the goddamn score comes out.
两分投篮
Two points, right there!
这就是该死的成绩
There's your goddamn score!
什么猫爬树  五五二十五
Goddamn cats crawling up trees, 5 times 5 is 25...
去他妈的这鬼地方
Fuck this place!
去他妈的
Fuck it!
真后悔
I feel bad.
让他失望了
I let him down.
胡说
That's crap, kid.
他以你为荣
He's proud of you.
多年的交情  我摸透他了
We're old friends,I know him as good as anybody.
他是聪明人
Smart fellow, ain't he?
绝顶聪明  曾是银行家
Smart as they come. He was a banker on the outside.
他究竟为何入狱?
What's he in here for anyway?
谋杀
Murder.
你少扯了
The hell, you say.
看他外表是想不到
You wouldn't think it to look at the guy.
捉到老婆跟高尔夫球教练在床  两个全干掉了
Caught his wife in bed with some golf pro. Greased them both.
怎么了？
What?
大约四年前
About four years ago...
我在托马斯顿监狱服刑
I was in Thomaston on a two-to-three stretch.
我偷了车
I stole a car.
实在愚蠢
It was a dumb-fuck thing to do.
刑期还剩半年时
About six months left to go...
来了个新室友
I get a new cellmate in.
厄摩·布拉奇
Elmo Blatch.
混蛋一个  大个子  神经质
Big, twitchy fucker.
谁都怕碰上这种室友  明白我的意思吧
IKind of roomie you pray you don't get. You know what I'm saying?
持械抢劫  服刑6至12年
Six-to-twelve, armed burglary.
他说他干过好几百票
Said he pulled hundreds of jobs.
想不到有那么神经的人  你放个响屁  他都能离地三尺
Hard to believe, high-strung as he was.You cut a loud fart, he jumped three feet.
他的嘴永远闭不上
Talked all the time too. That's the other thing. He never shut up.
他去过的地方
Places he'd been in...
犯过的罪行  玩过的女人
jobs he'd pulled, women he fucked.
甚至杀过的人
Even people he killed.
他说杀人
People who "gave him shit."
只是因为不爽
That's how he put it.
有一晚  就当玩笑
So one night, like a joke...
我问他  “你杀过谁？”
I say to him, "Elmo, who did you kill?"
他说——
So he says:
我在俱乐部收盘子
I got me this job one time, busing tables at a country club...
趁机观察阔人下手
so I could case all these bigrich pricks that come in.
我相中一人
So I pick out this guy...
在晚上
go in one night...
摸进他家
and do his place.
他醒来
He wakes up...
惹得我不爽
and gives me shit.
我就杀了他
So I killed him.
和他身边那骚货
Him and this tasty bitch he was with.
精彩的是
And that's the best part.
虽搞上这个高尔夫球教练
She's fucking this prick, see...
她却是个有夫之妇
this golf pro, but she's married to some other guy.
她老公  一个大银行家
Some hotshot banker.
成了替罪羊
And he's the one they pinned it on.
我从未听过如此惊人的故事
I have to say that's the most amazing story I ever heard.
最惊人的是你居然受骗
What amazes me most is you'd be taken in by it.
什么？
Sir?
显然汤米对你颇有好感
It's obvious this fellow Williams is impressed with you.
知道你很痛苦  自然想让你高兴
He hears your tale of woe and naturally wants to cheer you up.
他还年轻  脑筋不太灵光
He's young, not terribly bright.
根本不明白这反而会害苦了你
It's not surprising he wouldn't know what a state he put you in.
先生  他说的是实情
Sir, he's telling the truth.
就算真有厄摩这人
Let's say for the moment this Blatch does exist.
难道他会跪地哭诉  “是我杀的，我忏悔，”
You think he'd just fall to his knees and cry, "Yes, I did it. I confess.
“顺便再给我加个无期徒刑吧。”
By the way, add a life term to my sentence."
只要有汤米的证词 我就可以要求重审
With Tommy's testimony,I can get a new trial.
但你得找到厄摩
That's assuming Blatch is still there.
他可能早就出狱了
Chances are, he'd be released by now.
应该能查到住址  这可是机会
They'd have his last known address.It's a chance, isn't it?
你真是个木头
How can you be so obtuse?
什么？
What?
你说我什么？
What did you call me?
你笨蛋  我说错了吗？
Obtuse. Is it deliberate?
你别忘了身份
You're forgetting yourself.
俱乐部有厄摩的考勤卡
The country club will have his old timecards.
履历  税单
Records, W-2s with his name on them.
你爱幻想  那是你的事
If you want to indulge this fantasy, it's your business.
别给我添麻烦  面谈结束
Don't make it mine. This meeting is over.
我若出狱  绝不提你的事
If I got out, I'd never mention what happens here.
因为洗钱  与你同罪
I'd be as indictable as you for laundering that money.
不许你提钱这个字  混账东西
Don't ever mention money to me, you son of a bitch!
办公室里不许提
Not in this office...
到哪里都不许提  来人！
not anywhere. Get in here, now!
我只是想让你放心  没别的意思
I just wanted to put you at ease, that's all.
小号  一个月
Solitary. A month.
-你是怎么搞的？  -带走
-what's wrong with you? -Get him out of here.
这是我重获自由的机会  我的人生转机  你不懂吗？
This is my chance to get out! It's my life! Understand?!
带出去
Get him out!
小号  一个月
A month in the hole.
从没听过这么严厉的惩罚
That's the longest stretch I ever heard of.
都是我不对
It's all my fault.
胡说八道
Bullshit.
你没杀人  也没判安迪的罪
You didn't pull the trigger or convict him.
你是说安迪没罪？
Are you saying Andy is innocent?
他真的无辜？
I mean, for real innocent?
看来是这样
It looks that way.
我的天
Sweet Jesus.
他服刑多久了？
How long has he been here now?
47年进来  19年了
1947. What is that? Nineteen years.
-汤米的信  -我在这
-Williams, Thomas.  -Yeah, over here.
是什么？
What you got?
教育委员会来的
Board of Education.
-老小子寄出那考卷了  -看来是
-That son of a bitch mailed it. -Likely he did.
你是要拆开  还是就这么拿着傻看？
You going to open it or stand there with your thumb up your butt?
拿着傻看好些
Thumb up my butt sounds better.
把它还给我  你他妈的
Skeets, come on. Give me that, you shithead.
福洛
Floyd, come on.
瑞德
Red.
把它丢掉  好吗？
Will you throw that away, please?
狗屎  不赖
Well, shit.
他通过了  平均丙上
The kid passed. C + average.
跟你报个喜
Thought you'd like to know.
典狱长找你谈话
Warden wants to talk.
在这儿？
Out here?
他就是这样说的
That's what the man said.
典狱长？
Warden?
汤米？
汤米  这次会面要你保密
I'm asking you to keep this conversation just between us.
我良心深感不安
I feel awkward enough as it is.
他的判决出了问题
We got a situation here.
我想你明白
I think you can appreciate that.
是的
Yes, sir.
我明白
I sure can.
这件事真使我震惊
I tell you, son, this thing really came along and knocked my wind out.
我连觉都睡不好
It's got me up nights.That's the truth.
我该怎么做才好
The right thing to do...
有时连我也搞不清楚
sometimes it's hard to know what that is.
你了解吗？
Do you understand?
我需要你的协助  孩子
I need your help, son.
我要有……
If I'm going to move on this...
十足把握才能翻案
there can't be the least little shred of doubt.
我得知道
I have to know...
你所说是否实话
if what you told Dufresne was the truth.
是的
Yes, sir.
字字属实
Absolutely.
你愿在法官及陪审团前宣誓
Would you be willing to swear before a judge and jury...
并且手按圣经
with your hand on the Good Book...
在上帝跟前起誓吗？
and take an oath before Almighty God himself?
只要给我这个机会
Just give me that chance.
我也这样想
That's what I thought.
相信你已听说了
I'm sure by now you've heard.
真惨
Terrible thing.
年纪轻轻
A man that young...
刑期剩下不到一年还要逃
less than a year to go, trying to escape.
射杀他令海利伤透心
Broke Captain Hadley's heart to shoot him.
千真万确
Truly, it did.
我们只有忘掉这事
We just have to put it behind us.
继续过日子
Move on.
到此为止
I'm done.
我不干了
Everything stops.
你找别人帮你骗钱吧
Get someone else to run your scams.
一切照旧
Nothing stops.
一切
Nothing.
否则我要你生不如死
Or you will do the hardest time there is.
不再让警卫保护你
No more protection from the guards.
不再让你一人一间牢房  把你丢到鸡奸狂当中
I'll pull you out of that 1 -bunk Hilton and cast you down with the sodomites.
日日夜夜轮奸不休
You'll think you've been fucked by a train.
图书馆呢？
And the library?
没了
Gone.
用砖头封死
Sealed off, brick by brick.
在操场焚书
We'll have us a little book barbecue in the yard.
几里外都看得见火光
They'll see the flames for miles.
大家围着火跳红蕃舞
We'll dance around it like wild Injuns.
听懂了吗？
You understand me? Catching my drift?
我是笨蛋吗？
Or am I being obtuse?
再关他一个月  考虑清楚
Give him another month to think about it.
老婆说她很难了解我
My wife used to say I'm a hard man to know.
像一本合起来的书
Like a closed book.
她整天这样抱怨
Complained about it all the time.
她很漂亮
She was beautiful.
我那么爱她
God, I loved her.
我只是不擅表达
I didn't know how to show it, that's all.
是我杀了她
I killed her, Red.
枪不是我开的
I didn't pull the trigger...
但我害她离我远去
but I drove her away.
是我的脾气秉性
That's why she died, because of me...
害死了她
the way I am.
但你不是杀人犯
That don't make you a murderer.
只能说是差丈夫
Bad husband, maybe.
可以后悔  但你无罪
Feel bad about it if you want, but you didn't pull the trigger.
没错
No, I didn't.
别人干的
Somebody else did.
却由我受罚
And I wound up in here.
大概是我命薄
Bad luck, I guess.
谁都可能
It floats around.
沾染霉运
It's got to land on somebody.
刚好轮到我
It was my turn, that's all.
我被卷入龙卷风
I was in the path of the tornado.
只是没想到刮了这么久
I just didn't expect the storm would last as long as it has.
你有可能假释吗？
Think you'll ever get out of here?
我？
Me?
有吧
Yeah.
要等我老得发须花白
One day, when I got a long, white beard...
神智不清才行
and two or three marbles rolling around upstairs.
我跟你说我要去哪儿
I tell you where I'd go.
芝华塔尼欧
Zihuatanejo.
哪里？
Say what?
芝华塔尼欧
Zihuatanejo.
在墨西哥
It's in Mexico.
太平洋边的小地方
A little place on the Pacific Ocean.
-知道墨西哥人怎样说太平洋的吗？  -不知道
-You know what the Mexicans say about the Pacific? -No.
那是没有回忆的海洋
They say it has no memory.
我要在那度此余生
That's where I want to live the rest of my life.
没有回忆的温暖地
A warm place with no memory.
在海边
Open up a little hotel...
开个小旅馆
right on the beach.
买条破船
Buy some worthless old boat...
整修一新
and fix it up new.
载客出海
Take my guests out...
包船海钓
charter fishing.
芝华塔尼欧
Zihuatanejo.
你在那地方也大有可为
In a place like that, I could use a man that knows how to get things.
我在外头吃不开的
I don't think I could make it on the outside.
我一生都耗在肖申克
I been in here most of my life.
我已经体制化了
I'm an institutional man now.
就像老布
Just like Brooks was.
你别小看自己
You underestimate yourself.
我不这么认为
I don't think so.
我在牢里让你有求必应
In here I'm the guy who can get things for you, sure, but...
一出社会  电话簿里样样有
outside all you need is the Yellow Pages.
但我连查都不会查
Hell, I wouldn't know where to begin.
太平洋？
Pacific Ocean?
狗屁
Shit.
大的我心都毛了
Scare me to death, something that big.
我不会
Not me.
老婆和她情夫不是我杀的
I didn't shoot my wife,and I didn't shoot her lover.
我犯的错已还清
Whatever mistakes I made,I've paid for them and then some.
一间旅店  一叶扁舟
That hotel, that boat...
要求并不过份
I don't think that's too much to ask.
你不该有此妄想
You shouldn't be doing this to yourself.
完全痴人说梦
This is just shitty pipe dreams.
墨西哥和这儿
Mexico is way down there and you're in here...
天南地北
and that's the way it is.
说的没错
Yeah, right. That's the way it is.
远隔天涯海角
It's down there and I'm in here.
我猜是人就得二选一
I guess it comes down to a simple choice.
要么忙着活……
Get busy living...
要么忙着死
or get busy dying.
安迪
Andy.
瑞德
Red.
等你假释后  帮我个忙
If you ever get out of here,do me a favor.
没问题  你说
Sure, Andy. Anything.
巴克斯顿有个大草场  知道巴克斯顿吗？
There's a big hayfield up near Buxton.You know where Buxton is?
-那一带草场多得很  -有一处与众不同
-A lot of hayfields up there. -One in particular.
那里有长石墙  北端还有大橡树
It's got a long rock wall with a big oak tree at the north end.
美得像福斯特的诗
It's like something out of a Robert Frost poem.
我在那儿向她求婚
It's where I asked my wife to marry me.
我们去野餐
We went there for a picnic...
在橡树下做爱
and made love under that oak...
我开口  她首肯
and I asked and she said yes.
答应我  瑞德
Promise me, Red.
如果你终获假释
If you ever get out...
去找到那个地方
find that spot.
石墙底下有一块奇石
At the base of that wall, there's a rock that has no earthly business in Maine.
黑色火山玻璃石
Piece of black, volcanic glass.
底下埋着给你的东西
Something's buried under it I want you to have.
是什么？
What, Andy?
你埋着什么？
What's buried under there?
你搬开它
You'll have to pry it up...
就知道了
to see.
你们听我说
No, I'm telling you. The guy is...
他胡言乱语
He's talking funny.
我真担心他
I'm really worried about him.
我们要盯紧他
Let's keep an eye on him.
白天不要紧  晚上孤伶伶的
That's fine during the day, but at night he's all alone.
天哪
Oh, Lord.
怎么了？
What?
安迪今天到载货区
Andy come down to the loading dock today.
问我要一条绳子
He asked me for a length of rope.
-绳子？  -六尺长
Rope? Six feet long.
你给了他？
And you gave it to him.
为什么不给？
Sure. Why wouldn't I?
-天啊  赫伍  -我怎么想得到？
-Jesus! Heywood. -How was I supposed to know?
你忘了老布？
Remember Brooks Hatlen?
不  安迪不会寻短
Andy would never do that.
绝对不会
Never.
谁知道呢？
I don't know.
人的忍耐是有限度的
Every man has his breaking point.
动作快  我要回家
Lickety-split.Want to get home.
马上好了
Just about finished, sir.
今晚要存三笔
Three deposits tonight.
把衣物送洗
Get my stuff down to the laundry.
把鞋擦亮
And shine my shoes.
-要擦得雪亮  -是  先生
-I want them looking like mirrors. -Yes, sir.
你回来真好  安迪
It's good having you back.
没有你可差多了
Place wasn't the same without you.
熄灯
Lights out!
我也曾熬过孤寂长夜
I've had some long nights in stir.
独自在心中思东想西
Alone in the dark with nothing but your thoughts...
时间慢得如同刀割
time can draw out like a blade.
那是我毕生最长的一夜
That was the longest night of my life.
清点人数！
Give me a count!
-南三层到齐  -北四层到齐
Tier 3 south, clear!
北三层到齐
二层245没人
Man missing on tier 2, cell 245!
杜弗伦
Dufresne!
快出来 别耍花样
Come out. You're holding up the show!
等我找上门  可就重赏你的脑袋了
Don't make me come down or I'll thump your skull for you!
该死  我还得等你一个  你敢耽搁我时间
Damn it, you're putting me behind! I got a schedule to keep.
你最好是病了或是死了
You'd better be sick or dead in there. I shit you not!
听见没有？
You hear me?
噢  我的上帝
Oh, my Holy God.
这一分区每人都要问
I want every man on this cellblock questioned.
-先从他朋友开始  -谁？
-Start with that friend of his. -Who?
他
Him.
打开237
Open 237.
什么叫“他不见了”？  这算什么鬼话？
What do you mean, "He just wasn't here"? Don't say that to me.
你再说一次试试
Don't tell me that again.
但他真的不见了
But sir, he wasn't.
我没长眼睛吗？
I can see that, Haig! Think I'm blind?
你是这个意思？
Is that what you're saying?
-我眼瞎了？  -不敢  长官
-Am I blind, Haig? -No, sir!
你呢？ 你瞎了吗？
What about you. You blind?
-你说这是什么？  -昨晚的点名记录
-Tell me what this is. -Last night's count.
上面明明写着杜弗伦
You see Dufresne's name there? I sure do. Right there.
“杜弗伦”
"Dufresne."
熄灯时
He was in his cell...
他在牢里
at lights out.
早上应该也在才对
Reasonable he'd be here in the morning.
把他找到
I want him found.
一刻不能拖  现在就找！
Not tomorrow, not after breakfast. Now!
是  长官
Yes, sir.
搜人去  快点
Let's go. Move your butts.
站好
Stand.
你说
Well?
说什么？
Well, what?
你们俩成天粘在一起
I see you two all the time.You're thick as thieves, you are.
他一定说过什么
He must have said something.
报告典狱长
No, sir, Warden.
没有
Not a word.
那真是奇迹了
Lord, it's a miracle!
人像屁一样凭空消失
Man vanished like a fart in the wind.
不见踪影
Nothing left...
只剩一堆石头
but some damn rocks on a windowsill.
还有墙上那骚货  问问她吧
And that cupcake on the wall. Let's ask her.
也许她知道些什么
Maybe she knows.
你来说  短裤妞儿
What say there, fuzzy-britches? Feel like talking?
她不会说的
Guess not.
别人不说  为何她要说
Why should she be any different?
没错  你们有预谋
This is a conspiracy.
就是这样
That's what this is.
一个超级大阴谋
One big, damn conspiracy!
每个人都有份
And everyone's in on it!
包括她
Including her!
1966年
In 1966...
安迪·杜弗伦逃离……
Andy Dufresne escaped...
肖申克监狱
from Shawshank Prison.
狱方只寻获泥渍囚衣
All they found was a muddy set of prison clothes...
一块肥皂
a bar of soap...
和一把石锤
and an old rock hammer...
一把几乎解体的石锤
damn near worn down to the nub.
我曾夸口要花六百年才能挖通的隧道
I had thought it'd take a man 600 years to tunnel through the wall with it.
安迪花了不到20年
Old Andy did it in less than 20.
他喜爱研究地质
Oh, Andy loved geology.
碎石令他想一探究竟
I imagine it appealed to his meticulous nature.
刑期如同
An ice age here...
冰河时代
million years of mountain building there.
地质学探讨压力及时间
Geology is the study of pressure and time.
这就是凿通的关键——
That's all it takes, really.
压力
Pressure...
时间
and time.
和一张够大的海报
That and a big goddamn poster.
就像我说的
Like I said...
在牢里  没事也得找事做
in prison, a man will do anything to keep his mind occupied.
原来安迪的嗜好  就是把他的牢墙
Seems Andy's favorite hobby was toting his wall out into the exercise yard...
一次一把地搬到操场上
a handful at a time.
大概就在汤米死后
I guess after Tommy was killed...
安迪决定不再久留
Andy decided he'd been here long enough.
动作快  我要回家
Lickety-split.I want to get home.
马上就好
I'm just about finished, sir.
今晚要存三笔
Three deposits tonight.
安迪奉命行事
Andy did like he was told.
把鞋子擦得雪亮
Buffed those shoes to a high mirror-shine.
警卫都没注意
The guards simply didn't notice.
我也没有
Neither did I.
说真的
I mean, seriously...
谁会注意别人的鞋子
how often do you really look at a man's shoes?
安迪就这样爬向自由
Andy crawled to freedom through 500 yards...
在恶臭中匍匐五百码
of shit-smelling foulness I can't even imagine.
换我才不干呢
Or maybe I just don't want to.
五百码
Five hundred yards.
有五个足球场那么长
That's the length of five football fields.
接近半英里
Just shy of half a mile.
次日清晨  在拉寇儿坦露她的秘密之时
The next morning, right about the time Raquel was spilling her secret...
一个从未现世的人
a man nobody ever laid eyes on before...
走进缅因国家银行
strolled into the Maine National Bank.
在那之前  他不是实体
Until that moment, he didn't exist.
-只存在于文件上  -有何贵干？
-Except on paper. -May I help you?
他各种证件都有
He had all the proper ID...
驾照  出生证  社会保险卡
driver's license, birth certificate, Social Security card...
签名分毫不差
And the signature was a spot-on match.
失去您的生意令我真心遗憾
I must say I'm sorry to be losing your business.
祝您侨居愉快
I hope you'll enjoy living abroad.
谢谢
Thank you.
一定的
I'm sure I will.
这是银行本票  就这样吗？
Here's your cashier's check, sir. Will there be anything else?
麻烦你
Please.
帮我寄出去好吗？
Would you add this to your outgoing mail?
乐意之至
I'd be happy to.
-再会  -走好
-Good day, sir. -Good day.
那天上午史帝文先后去了十多家银行
Mr. Stevens visited nearly a dozen banks in the Portland area that morning.
总共加起来
All told, he blew town...
提走了诺顿37万美金
with better than $370,000 of Warden Norton's money.
作为十九年冤狱的补偿
Severance pay for 19 years.
早上好 这里是《波特兰号角日报》
Good morning, Portland Daily Bugle.
你是海利吗？  你有权保持沉默
Byron Hadley? You have the right to remain silent.
从现在起 你所说的一切 都将可能成为呈堂证供
If you give up this right, anything you say can be held against you in court.
当时我没有在场  后来听说
I wasn't there to see, but I hear Byron Hadley sobbed like a girl...
海利被人带走的时候  哭得像个娘们儿
when they took him away.
诺顿却无意乖乖就范
Norton had no intention of going that quietly.
诺顿
Samuel Norton.
诺顿  我们有拘捕令  开门
We have a warrant for your arrest. Open up.
把门打开
Open the door.
我不清楚是哪一把
I'm not sure which key.
别自找麻烦  诺顿
Make it easy on yourself, Norton!
我猜他脑中最后一件事
I like to think the last thing that went through his head...
除了枪子儿
other than that bullet...
就是在想安迪为何能整倒他
was to wonder how the hell Andy Dufresne ever got the best of him.
典狱长呜呼后不久
Not long after the warden deprived us of his company...
我收到一张明信片
I got a postcard in the mail.
没写字  但有邮戳
It was blank, but the postmark said...
来自德州汉考克堡
Fort Hancock, Texas.
汉考克堡
Fort Hancock...
就在边境线上
right on the border.
安迪就是从那里出境的
That's where Andy crossed.
驾着敞蓬车驶向南方
When I picture him heading south in his own car with the top down...
想到这画面就令我开怀大笑
it always makes me laugh.
安迪·杜弗伦
Andy Dufresne...
爬过肮脏的下水道
who crawled through a river of shit...
出来已焕然一新
and came out clean on the other side.
安迪·杜弗伦
Andy Dufresne...
向太平洋驶去
headed for the Pacific.
海利掐住他喉咙说
Hadley's got him by the throat, right?
“他活的不耐烦了。”
He says, "I believe this boy's about to have himself an accident."
老友们常聊起他
Those of us who knew him best talk about him often.
他那些惊人之举
I swear, the stuff he pulled...
“请我朋友喝啤酒吧……”
"My friends could use a couple of beers."
他真的做到了！
And he got it!
有时我会感伤
Sometimes it makes me sad, though...
他的离去
Andy being gone.
我不得不提醒自己
I have to remind myself that...
有些鸟儿是注定不会被关在牢笼里的
some birds aren't meant to be caged.
它们的每一片羽毛都闪耀着自由的光辉
Their feathers are just too bright.
当它们盘旋飞离之时
And when they fly away...
你会由衷地祝贺它们获得自由
the part of you that knows it was a sin to lock them up does rejoice.
无奈的是
But still...
你得继续在这乏味之地苟活
the place you live in is that much more drab and empty that they're gone.
我真怀念这位友伴
I guess I just miss my friend.
请坐
Please sit down.
埃利斯·博伊德·瑞丁
Ellis Boyd Redding...
根据你的材料 你的终身监禁已经服满40年
your files say you've served 40 years of a life sentence.
你改过自新了吗？
You feel you've been rehabilitated?
改过自新？
Rehabilitated?
噢  让我想想
Well, now, let me see.
我不大明白这个词的含义
I don't have any idea what that means.
就是说准备好重返社会
It means you're ready to rejoin society...
我当然明白你的意思  年轻人
I know what you think it means, sonny.
对我而言  这只是个术语
To me it's just a made-up word.
政客发明的术语
A politician's word so that...
好让你们穿西装打领带
young fellas like yourself can wear a suit and a tie...
有活干
and have a job.
你到底想了解什么？
What do you really want to know?
我后悔犯罪吗？
Am I sorry for what I did?
你后悔吗？
Well, are you?
我没有一天不后悔
There's not a day goes by I don't feel regret.
但并非因为关在这里 也不为讨好你们
Not because I'm in here or because you think I should.
回首前尘往事
I look back on the way I was then...
那个
a young...
犯下重罪的小笨蛋
stupid kid who committed that terrible crime.
我想跟他沟通
I want to talk to him.
我试图讲道理
I want to try and talk some sense to him.
让他明了
Tell him the way things are.
但我办不到
But I can't.
那个少年早就不见了
That kid's long gone...
只剩下我垂老之躯
and this old man is all that's left.
我得接受事实
I got to live with that.
改过自新？
Rehabilitated?
狗屁不通的词儿
It's just a bullshit word.
盖章吧  别浪费我的时间
So you go on and stamp your forms,sonny, and stop wasting my time.
告诉你一句实话
Because to tell you the truth...
我他妈的不在乎
I don't give a shit.
你的 小姐
Here you go, miss.
可以上厕所吗？
Restroom break?
别一尿尿就来报告  要去就去  懂吗?
You don't need to ask me every time you need to go take a piss. Just go.
是
Yes.
我报告了40年
Forty years I've been asking permission to piss.
不报告  一滴也挤不出
I can't squeeze a drop without say-so.
我得面对一个残酷的事实
There's a harsh truth to face.
在狱外我根本混不下去
No way I'm going to make it on the outside.
我一心想违犯假释
All I do anymore is think of ways to break my parole...
也许就能重返肖申克
so maybe they'd send me back.
活在恐惧中真是糟糕
Terrible thing, to live in fear.
老布体会过
Brooks Hatlen knew it.
他看透了
Knew it all too well.
我只想回到有意义的地方
All I want is to be back where things make sense.
不必整天担惊受怕
Where I won't have to be afraid all the time.
只有一件事阻止了我
Only one thing stops me.
我向安迪做过承诺
A promise I made to Andy.
到了
There it is.
非常感谢您
Much obliged, sir.
“亲爱的瑞德：”
Dear Red:
“见到这封信的时候，你已经出狱了。”
If you're reading this,you've gotten out...
“既然走了这么远的路，干脆再走远一点吧。”
and if you've come this far,maybe you'd come a bit further.
“你还记得那个地方的名字，是吗？”
You remember the name of the town, don't you?
“芝华塔尼欧。”
Zihuatanejo.
“请来帮我实现计划，”
I could use a good man to help me get my project on wheels.
“我备妥棋盘等着你。”
I'll keep an eye out for you, and the chessboard ready.
“记住，瑞德，”
Remember, Red...
“心怀希望是一件好事，”
hope is a good thing...
“也许是最好的事。”
maybe the best of things.
“心怀希望，就永远都有希望。”
And no good thing ever dies.
“希望这封信，能让我再次见到你，”
I will be hoping that this letter finds you...
“一个健在的你。”
and finds you well.
“你的朋友”
Your friend...
“安迪”
Andy.
“要么忙着活，”
"Get busy living...
“要么忙着死。”
or get busy dying."
这话真他妈的精辟
That's goddamn right.
这是生平第二次
For the second time in my life...
我又犯了罪
I'm guilty of committing a crime.
违反假释出城
Parole violation.
我怀疑警方会设路障抓我
Of course I doubt they'll toss up any roadblocks for that.
不过我这种老贼大可免了
Not for an old crook like me.
去德州汉考克堡  谢谢
Fort Hancock, Texas, please.
我激动得不能安坐或思考
I find I'm so excited I can barely sit still or hold a thought in my head.
我想  只有真正的自由人
I think it's the excitement only a free man can feel.
在踏上远征那一刻  才会生出这种
A free man at the start of a long journey...
即将揭开未来神秘面纱的激动心情吧
whose conclusion is uncertain.
我希望能顺利跨越边境
I hope I can make it across the border.
我希望能跟重逢老友握握手
I hope to see my friend and shake his hand.
我希望太平洋如梦中一般蓝
I hope the Pacific is as blue as it has been in my dreams.
我希望……
I hope.